<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to Monsieur Talon's plea published at Paris.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B17145</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12786487</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205164</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240954487</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3365</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12786487</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B17145)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1518:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to Monsieur Talon's plea published at Paris.</title>
                  <author>Talon, Denis, 1627-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  France --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Popes --  Temporal power.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205164:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205164:1"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO Monsieur Talon's PLEA, Published at <hi>PARIS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exod. 21.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Qui maledixerit Patri suo.</p>
               <p>He that curseth his Father.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exod. 22.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Principi populi tui non maledices.</p>
               <p>You shall not curse the head of your people.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ambros. in Psalm. 118.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Vere frustra impugnatur, qui apud impios &amp; infidos impietatis arcessitur, cum fidei sit Magister.</p>
               <p>He truly is opposed in vain, who by the Wicked and Ʋnfaithfull is aspersed with impiety, when he is indeed the master of our Faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>With Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:205164:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205164:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Answer to Monsieur</hi> Talon's <hi>Plea, Published at</hi> Paris.</head>
            <p>HEre has appeared some days ago, a Plea of <hi>Monsieur Talon's,</hi> at the head of a Decree of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> issued against a Bull of our Lord the Pope, which Excommunicates all those who under pretence of pretended Franchises, shelter all sorts of Villains, Banditts, and Assassinates, and hinder the course of Justice in the City of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this Paper had not appeared publickly in <hi>Paris</hi> in the name of the Parliament, we should never have believed that under a Prince of that wisdom and Zeal for the Catholick Faith, as his Most Christian Majesty has ever appeared to be, any man durst have published such a Pamphlet as this, that looks rather like a defamatory Libell, fill'd with injuries against the Pope and the Apostolick See, then like the Plea of an Advocate-General, that has spent his Age in the Profession of Eloquence and Law.</p>
            <p>This Magistrate in his Youth, spoke of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> but from the Memorialls of <hi>Dr Launoy,</hi> who never had other end in his Writings then to lessen the Sovereign Authority of the Pope: It was hoped that Age and Experience would have tempered by this time that Critical and Morose humour of his, which made him heretofore Write with so little Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Sacred See.</p>
            <p>And we might have thought that the Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> having so vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously remonstrated, and so notably complained of a Plea of his he made above Twenty years ago, in which he had advanced Propositions so abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely Erroneous, and so injurious to the Church of God, that the Bishops of <hi>France</hi> openly Taxed 'em with Heresy and Schism, he would not have presumed to have pull'd upon himself again; not only the just indignation of those Venerable Prelates, but indeed the Clamour of the whole Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, for Violating that Sacred Respect, which has ever from all good Christians been due to the Vicar of Christ, and the Visible Head of the Church.</p>
            <p>Besides, the Advocate speaking upon this occasion, only in Complyance with the Ministers of the King, we had some ground to expect more Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty from him. But whether it were that he acted by order of the Court,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205164:3"/>or that he Indulged that Extravagant humour of his, ever contrary to the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> 'tis certain he never with more Liberty was transported against the Pope and the Sacred See, then in this last Plea of his. We might have thought that in a matter of this importance, and a Controversy that has made such a Noise in the World, as this of the Franchises has done, a Man of Learning and Parts, would have examined the matter in question to the bottom; would have established the Pretensions of <hi>France</hi> by Arguments of some force; would have brought us Presidents from Authentique History; would have given us Reasons well grounded in Law, and so with some Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour at least have asserted those unjust and Chymerical pretensions which aim at the power of exercising Acts of Sovereignty in the middle of other Lands then his own, and in the Capital City of another Prince's Dominions: for indeed the right which <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> maintains, is nothing else but this: To be able to tye the hands of a Sovereign Prince in his own State; to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to exercise an Absolute Sovereignty in a place where he has no Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at all: to be able to give shelter, and allow impunity to all Criminals whatsoever: to be able to Authorize all sorts of Disorders in a City which (as <hi>Monsieur Lavardin</hi> was pleas'd to call it) is the general Countrey of all good Christians, and where consequently good Order and exact Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are more necessary then in any part of the World. In a word, 'tis to be able to expose that infinity of Persons which come to <hi>Rome</hi> from all parts of the World, to all sorts of Insolencies and Injuries without their being any ways able to demand Justice or to secure themselves. This in short is the substance of that right of Franchises or Priviledges which the Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of <hi>France</hi> pretends to have at his particular House within the Walls of <hi>Rome.</hi> A right so odious and so abominable, if we consider the consequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces well, that though the Most <hi>Christian</hi> King had all the right in the world on his side, yet that Piety and Justice which God and the World expects from such a Prince as he, would oblige him voluntarily to renounce it, that he might not be one day forced to answer both to God and Man for that infinity of Crimes and Villanies that this pretended Priviledge of his not only permits, but Authorizes too. And yet in this Discourse of <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> we cannot find so much as the least Argument, nor proof of any thing he affirms: We see nothing here of that Pompons and borrowed eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which he makes so much use of in his other Discourses; He makes but little use here of those large common places, of the enterprises of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of the Priviledges of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church: this Plea of his is nothing but a bitter and perpetual Satyr against the Pope and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred See of <hi>Rome.</hi> He never goes about to prove (as so bold an Assertor of Novelty ought to have done) that from the first beginning of the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205164:3"/>of <hi>France,</hi> the King had always enjoyed such a Privilege as this in <hi>Rome,</hi> never offers to tell us how and in what manner those Priviledges of <hi>France</hi> by their Kings were made use of in all times; but thinks it suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to say, that That Privilege is a Right of the <hi>French</hi> Crown, from which this King desires the world to believe he will never depart. He affirms that neither Kings, nor their Ambassadors can be Excommunicated by the Pope, but never takes upon him to prove it, no more then he does to shew us that pretended injustice of the Interdict of the Church of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> in <hi>Rome:</hi> he thinks it seems a shorter and faciler way of dispute, barely to say with a definitive Gravity, <hi>Here's a great abuse; This Wounds the Liberty of</hi> France; but reasons that might satisfy such Intelligent and Learned men as may not only read, but search perhaps into the bottom of such a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversy as this, he gives none at all. So that in all appearance this will at last be the fate of this famous Advocate so much vaunted of in the <hi>Gazette</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> that this Plea of his will give all Hereticks and Enemies of the Church an excellent occasion to triumph, All Learned and Intelligent men good ground to despise him; All Good Catholicks that are firm in the Communion of the Catholick Church sufficient cause to look upon him with Indignation and Horror: Evil men themselves will blush at his Confidence, and the Good will not be able to read him without tears; when they shall consider that under a King that professes so great moderation and wisdom, such a declaimer as this shall be suffered to appear with such Insolence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the head of the Church, and take the Confidence to Publish such Schismatick Propositions against the Pope, and the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this above all must needs be to all Good Catholicks a most insup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable grief, to see that those very men in whose hands the King trusts all the Ecclesiastical affairs of his Kingdom, as well as those chief Ministers he employs at <hi>Rome,</hi> are so far from blaming these rash and ill-considered Propositions of this Advocate-General, that they are the principal fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of this Rebellion against the Sacred See, the only Authors and Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of those unworthy calumnies against his Holiness, and the men that most rejoyce to see that grand Reputation which this Excellent Pope through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his whole Reign by so many great and glorious actions had acquired, not only amongst Catholicks, but in all Nations else, even among Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks themselves, whilst his Enemies honour him, whilst Separatists love him, whilst all Christians admire him; that That Reputation of his, should be by Catholicks publickly, and shamefully torn in the face of a Catholick, Country, and under a Most Christian King.</p>
            <p>I have endeavoured all I can to put this Libell into some kind of order, that I might give the Reader a true Idea of the whole piece, and so
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205164:4"/>the more exactly have examined it some and some; but this Advocate is so little a Friend to Order and Method in what he Writes, that we must refute his Arguments but as we find 'em, and take 'em as they come.</p>
            <p>His whole Plea seems to consist of these Principal Heads.</p>
            <p>The Advocate's outrageous injuries against the Pope; His Complaints of the Pope's Conduct in the affairs of <hi>France;</hi> The Errors he broaches against the Authority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, that Mother and Mistress of all others; The pittifull Chicanneries he employs to give the King of <hi>France</hi> those Cymerical Rights contrary to all Laws Humane and Divine, and such as the basest of Flatterers never allow'd him 'till now.</p>
            <p>This is as near as I can collect the sum of his Plea. The first Calumny with which <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> reproaches the Pope, is this: That his Holiness has been conceived this many years to have had a design to declare himself Enemy to <hi>France,</hi> still favouring those who either were Enemies, or were jealous at least of the greatness and power of that King. Since this Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate has aspersed his Holiness with so black a Calumny as this, it might be very well expected he should give us some proof of what he says; let him shew therefore what leagues the Pope has made with the Enemies of <hi>France.</hi> Let him tell us in what ill Enterprize, or in what violent action this Pope has been concerned. But he can shew us no such thing. This Pope never took any thing so much to heart as the Uniting of the Christian Princes, nor ever desired any thing more then to give the King of <hi>France</hi> all the signs imaginable of his particular esteem, and Paternal affection. As for Leagues this Pope never made any, but that Holy one of as many Christian Princes as could, by the best endeavours he was able to use, be induced to oppose the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperour, that Common Enemy of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom; where those miraculous Successes of the Christian Arms have sufficiently demonstrated how much the endeavours of so good a Pope were seconded by extraordinary blessings from God. Though his Holiness in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed could not oftentimes without great Tenderness and trouble behold how too too easily a Prince otherwise so Pious, and Just, as his Most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Majesty always appeared, whilst he was pleased to follow his own Royal inclinations, did at last absolutely abandon himself to the pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Councells of some of his Ecclesiastical Ministers.</p>
            <p>With what Charity did this great Pope represent to his Christian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty the Injustice Committed, and Injuries done in his name, by extending the <hi>Regalia</hi> upon four Provinces that had ever been free? With what grief did he see so many Holy Bishops and good Priests of the Church, Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted so bitterly in the name of his Christian Majesty, for no other Crime then defending the immunities of their several Churches, which the Bishops
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205164:4"/>of <hi>France</hi> had for near these Eight Hundred years so generously defended, and so stoutly maintained, and which <hi>Monsieur de Marca,</hi> as devoted as he was to the Court, yet compell'd by the force of truth it self, did ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously confess; with what grief did he think of the dissolving of the Institute of the <hi>Nunns</hi> of the <hi>Infancy,</hi> which had been Authoriz'd by the Bishops of the Diocess, approved by Popes, confirmed by Letters Patents, and that contrary to all Order, and without any regular form of Justice?</p>
            <p>What grief was it to him to see on one side the Destruction of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastery of <hi>Charonne,</hi> and on the other side, the violent Establishment of Abbesses in the Houses of the <hi>Ʋrbanists,</hi> contrary both to Civil and Canon Law? What grief was it to him, to see what continual Usurpations the Lay-Judges made in <hi>France,</hi> as well upon the Liberties, as Jurisdictions of the Church?</p>
            <p>What grief must it have been to him to see how shamefully the Church of <hi>France</hi> was forced to serve under the Yoke of those Persons whose Lives were but too well known; that a Church, I say, where nothing but Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is talked of, should be so enslaved to Parliaments which make no scruple at all to take Cognizance of the most Spiritual matters, and to exercise their Jurisdiction upon all holy things with more haughtiness in their Usurped Power, then the legallest General Councils ever did, or the Sovereign Popes themselves?</p>
            <p>What a grief was it to him to see all the Principal Abbeys as well of the conquered Countries, as of the ample Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> given in great <hi>Commendum</hi> without the Authority of the Church, and contrary to all Canon Law; to see what manifest intrusions were Authorized in obliging the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops to remove and abandon their Lawfull Spouses, those Flocks to which they properly belonged, into the hands of new Bishops nominated only by the King, whilst they went themselves to govern other Churches that did not belong to their care. To see a Bishop transferr'd make his own Vicar; to see the Chapters, in the vacancies of Bishopricks, not only forced against their will, but in spight of their Conscience too, name for Grand Vicar those whom the King intends to bestow the Bishopricks upon, and banish all such Prebends as refuse to Elect the person which the King had designed to promote.</p>
            <p>What trouble was it to him to think that the Bishops of <hi>France,</hi> which formerly by their extraordinary respect, and profoundest submission, were so intimately united with the Head of the Church, now instead of apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselves thither, should declare open War against him? As they did in the Letter to the King sent from the extraordinary Assembly of the Year 1680. Subscribed by all the Bishops, when it never had been read by half
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205164:5"/>those that were there. And again in those deliberations that were taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Authority of the Sacred See in the Assembly of 1682. Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings very different from those the Clergy of <hi>France</hi> at the meeting of the Estates in the Year 1616. published to the World by that admirable mouth of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, Cardinal <hi>Peronne,</hi> or from those Articles which were drawn up in the Year 1625. for the re-establishment of the Catholick Faith, and for the restoring the Ecclesiastical Discipline in the Kingdom of <hi>France.</hi> But then the <hi>French</hi> Prelates acted of themselves, and animated with the Spirit of Religion: in these later Assemblies influenced by the Impression of the Court, they acted more like a Caball then an Ecclesiastical Assembly, rather as their fear then as their Reason and Learning directed 'em, which made a Bishop the least scrupulous perhaps in that Assembly of 1682. (giving a Friend of his an account of what had passed there) say not much amiss, that those <hi>French</hi> Bishops had at that time parted with, besides their Wealth, their Honour and Consciences too.</p>
            <p>And what trouble do you think it was to him to see the Clergy of <hi>France</hi> once so Orthodoxal and exemplar, that they were by their Piety, and Learning, and Sacerdotal vigour known and distinguish'd from all other men, now so fallen from that Primitive Spirit of theirs, that the Bishops poorly and shamefully abandon their Rights, and the Priviledges of their Churches without ever daring so much as to open their mouths to complain?</p>
            <p>But above all, it must needs afflict that Father and Protector of Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity the Head of the Christian Church, to see so many good Priests, so many Learned Doctors proscrib'd, persecuted, imprison'd, banish'd, and driven from their Benefices and Employments by Letters under the Kings Seal without any Legal Process, without any reason in the world, nay sometimes without so much as acquainting the Bishop of the Diocess to whom they belonged: and this only upon those general Accusations of <hi>Jansenism,</hi> which at present, it seems, must be the common ruine of all those good Priests, and all those innocent men which do not relish at Court. Nay though these Ecclesiasticks, to justify themselves positively declare that they do absolutely condemn, and have ever condemned the Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in those five condemned Propositions of <hi>Jansenius;</hi> yet they are not to be believed, though certainly in matters of Religion no man without a high injustice can but believe that profession of Faith which every one makes for himself. But they continue still to upbraid 'em, that they are of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball; that they are under suspition of <hi>Jansenism;</hi> that their Moral is rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and with an infinity of such other terms, which signifies no more in effect but that they are Persons which do not please those who have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205164:5"/>in the Court of <hi>France</hi> the super-intendency of Ecclesiastical affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> complains very much of the <hi>Roman Inquisition:</hi> But if on the one side he did but know how things are carried at that Tribunal, with what attention they hear the accusations that are brought against any man, with what application every mans justification and answers are examined; with what maturity they decide; and on the other side do but reflect how at present they try, and judge the Ecclesiasticks in <hi>France;</hi> how they are Condemned without ever being heard, without ever being made acquainted with what their Adversaries have against 'em, without over being confronted with their Accusers and Witnesses, nay without so much as consulting the Bishops of the Diocess in the matter at all, in a word without any form or semblance of juridical process, and only upon a bare letter of — that in this manner so many irreprehensible Ecclesiasticks should be detained in horrid Prisons, or sent away to the remotest and savagest parts of the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> without Money, without any help or comfort whatsoever, and without the least hope of ever returning to their Country again, and without knowing all this while upon what account they suffer. <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> as much as he is prepossess'd, would, I believe, conclude in his heart at least, though he should not vouchsafe to own the truth publickly, that in <hi>France</hi> we bear a heavier and much more insupportable Yoke then those at <hi>Rome;</hi> and that the Inquisition of those supreme Ministers, in whose hands his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty of <hi>France</hi> is pleased to intrust the Ecclesiastical affairs of this Nation, is without comparison harder than the Inquisition of either <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> which in <hi>France</hi> they rail at so much, without ever knowing any thing of the proceedings of those Courts: and alas! without making all this while the least reflection upon those so violent and irregular proceedings, which are used in <hi>France</hi> against the best and most irreprehensible men, when any of them have the misfortune to have for their Enemies those which are in favour at Court.</p>
            <p>The Pope saw long ago these Mischiefs, and sees 'em still, with an infinity of other Evills which would be too tedious to relate. He has sigh'd for 'em before Almighty God, he has represented 'em to the King in his briefs, with all the tenderness that his paternal Charity could sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest; some of 'em he declared by his Nuncio's. And if this be, to be Enemy of <hi>France,</hi> to be tenderly concerned at their Miseries, to sigh for 'em in the presence of God, to advertise the King out of his Fatherly care, that remedies might be had: If this be, to be Enemy of <hi>France,</hi> to defend the Liberties of the Church, to desire the Reformation of the Clergy, to endeavour the ease of Persons unjustly afflicted, then we will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205164:6"/>yield to <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> that the Pope is a declared Enemy of <hi>France;</hi> though certainly he can be Enemy no otherwise to that State, then a carefull Phisician is to the Patient he endeavours to recover; or then a wise and affectionate Father is to his Child, when he endeavours to make him sensible of his faults.</p>
            <p>The Second head of <hi>Monsieur Talon's</hi> complaint against the Pope, (if yet the Complaint be his) for it has so little report with what goes before, and that which comes after, that it looks as if it had been inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the discourse: however it was, he complains in his Second head of this Plea, that the Pope entertains particular correspondence with all those who formerly were the declared Disciples of <hi>Jansenius;</hi> that he loads them with his graces and favours, gives great Elogiums of 'em, and declares himself their Protector. But who are those declared Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Jansenius</hi> upon whom the Pope heaps so many graces and favours, of whom he gives such Elogiums, and of whom he declares himself the Protector? <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> ought to clear us that point; but let him have a care when he does it, that he do not appear rather a Calumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, then any thing else, and that he do not openly contradict those Declarations of the King, which forbid him to look upon any of those as <hi>Jansenists</hi> or <hi>Sectaries</hi> either, who have submitted to the Constitutions of the Pope against <hi>Jansenius,</hi> and have not any ways been publickly convicted or condemned upon that account, by the censures of an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Judge.</p>
            <p>But that you may see his insolence to the full, he has the Confidence to affirm that the Pope supports and foments the Caball of the <hi>Jansenists.</hi> And this he is suffered to say in a most Christian Kingdom. This is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to be placed at the head of a Decree that bears the name of the most Christian King. And such a Calumny as this goes on and spreads without the least notice taken, or any thought had of making satisfaction to the head of the Church. And is this the respect we shew the Pope? Is it thus the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> acknowledges him? What Priest or Bishop then, let him be as Innocent as he will, can ever hope to secure himself from such calumnies as these, If the Pope, and such a Pope as this, so Pious, so Zealous to maintain the Catholick Faith in its purity, as his present Holiness is, cannot escape such publick and impudent calumnies as these?</p>
            <p>But 'tis not enough to make the Pope appear a favourer of Hereticks in <hi>France,</hi> but that they may render him odious too in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spain. Monsieur Talon</hi> complains of a supine Negligence and strange backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in the Pope, because he did not suppress the <hi>Quietists</hi> more speedily
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205164:6"/>then he did; And yet with what Zeal and Indignation has he proceeded against that Infamous Sect? What greater care then has been, could have been taken to get that bad Doctrine Condemned, since the first time that the Impostor <hi>Molina</hi> was first convicted? 'Tis true his Holiness, when any Priests were to be judged, would not suffer Sentence to be too much precipitated against 'em, nor suffer his Judges to act by humour, or as if they were influenced by a Caball; He thought it fit to make some difference betwixt the Author of a Sect, and those, who (deluded by such Impostors) with too much obstinacy perhaps had adher'd to the Errors of other men, surprized it may be, with the false appearance of the Piety, which the <hi>Molinists</hi> made a great shew of for above Twenty years. In all which the Pope has done no more then the Canons of the Church, and the Decretal Letters of his Predecessors have prescribed. But because the Pope does not think fit to crush persons of the Highest Quality, and men of Exemplar Piety, who have ever owned an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and faithfull Submission to the Sacreed See, and to the Church; Therefore if we believe <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> he carries himself sleepily, and as if he were in a Lethargy, towards the <hi>Quietists.</hi> When the Pope, some years ago by a solemn Decree condemned the infamous Errours of the corrupted Moral of the <hi>Casuists,</hi> the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> opposed it, and forbid the Publication of the Decree because the Inquisition was mentioned in it. But when the Pope does not think fit to Sacrifice Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Prelates and men of an Extraordinary Merit to the passion of their Adversaries, and because he thinks fit to do nothing without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation, and after a strict and serious examination in his Judgment of the <hi>Molinists,</hi> they complain he does not act with ardour enough; and they are impatient till they can improve the Decisions of the Inquisition now, as odious as that Tribunal was to <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> upon all other occasions, and especially when it condemned the Errours and Laxities of the bad <hi>Casuists</hi> of our time.</p>
            <p>Finally this able Orator finds great fault that we look upon this Pope as a Model of Piety and Virtue. He takes all those for Disciples of <hi>Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senius,</hi> he says, which erect such Altars to his Holiness: But truly this Magistrate must needs be mightily transported with Passion, or strangely prepossest to believe that this Pope has no other Esteemers nor Admirers but that despicable handfull of men here and there dispersed, and hid up and down, which to day are called <hi>Jansenists;</hi> when all <hi>Europe</hi> mean while honours him with so much admiration as it does, and looks upon him as a Pope which God out of his extraordinary mercy has sent his Church in so corrupted an Age as this, to let us see that his hand is not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205164:7"/>straitned, and that he can at all times raise up faithfull Pastours to his Church, and men according to his own heart, though the World be not worthy of them.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>Rome</hi> before his promotion to the Sacred See, look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him as a Person the most worthy of that Supreme Dignity of any in the world. And the effects God be thanked, have answered the hopes which all men had of him then. That unconcernedness of his in all Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Affairs so well known to the world, as well in regard of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in particular, as of his Family, who are none of 'em now any richer then when he was first promoted to the Papacy. That continual and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest application to put the Apostolical Chamber in better order and into a better Condition which for these many years had been exhausted and beggar'd. His Indefatigable care and pains for uniting the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> against the common Enemy of Christendom, the Treasure that he has so profusely spent to that purpose, and for the universal good of the Christian World. The strange blessings of God that followed his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in such total Victories over that Enemy of Christianity, and that panick fear the Infidels minds were so often filled with; in which the hand of God so evidently appeared: the safety of <hi>Germany</hi> which that Emperour owes chiefly to the glorious endeavours of this great Pope. Then his great aversion from all kind of Pride; the freest from Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism of any; His exemplar Piety always equal and always the same; his great firmness of Mind, uncapable of being shaken; to say nothing of all his other more Personal Virtues, which those who are about him are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to know then we, at this distance, can do. All these things, I say, must needs be look'd upon by the world as the admirable effects of his high and extraordinary Virtues; and will be doubtless the eternal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of that Glory of his which the Envy and Malignity of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies will never be able to obscure.</p>
            <p>After all those black Calumnies thrown upon the Pope, <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> makes yet other Complaints against his Conduct in the <hi>Gallican</hi> Affairs: but that which he insists upon most, and where he hopes to have the greatest advantage, is that his Holiness refuses to supply the vacant Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopricks of <hi>France</hi> upon the Kings nomination, as he used in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to do; that above the third part of the Churches of <hi>France</hi> are at this time without Pastours, and that if the Pope will not execute the Concordat, his Majesty may Lawfully break it too on his side, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Bishops in the name of the People, of which he is undoubtedly the head. Would to God the Concordat were but as Religiously executed in <hi>France</hi> as it is in <hi>Rome,</hi> there would not then be seen in this Kingdom of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205164:7"/>
               <hi>France</hi> so many abuses as all good men have so long grieved to see; and which indeed are the more deplorable, because there is no remedy to be had.</p>
            <p>But to come to the Fact in Question, the Pope never did refuse to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for those Bishopricks where the King had nominated, if the Persons named were so qualified, as the Canons and Concordat require.</p>
            <p>But the Pope pretends that by the words of the Concordat, it belongs to him and his Successors, to examine whether the Persons named by the King have the Qualities required, or no: and that those that have them not, lose for that very reason immediately the right which they have by the King's nomination, who is obliged within three Months after such exceptions made by the Pope to nominate again such others as shall have the Qualities required. But the Pope is not bound to shew cause why he refuses, and therefore no body can Judge of the reasons of his refusal but himself. 'Tis true, the Pope ought not to make such refusal without a Lawfull cause: his Conscience indeed is charged with it in the sight of God: but no Power upon Earth has any right to take Cognizance of, much less, to Judge of that refusal of the Pope's, or to force him to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish those that are unworthy and not qualified for the place; or to fall off from the Concordat upon that account. It is no difficult thing in this to justify the right of the Pope, we need but only look upon the text of the Concordat, and then take notice of what has pass'd since in <hi>France;</hi> we shall find in the Letters of Cardinal <hi>D'Ossat,</hi> that <hi>René Benoist</hi> Confessor to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, was never able to get the Pope's Bulls for the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoprick of <hi>Troyes,</hi> for which he had been nominated by the King, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all the instance that was made by the Ambassadours of the King and all the Cardinals of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And no body, I think, can be ignorant of the Story of that famous Abbot (whose name shall be here concealed) that was nominated for a certain Bishoprick by the late King of <hi>France Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth with the greatest Elogiums that could be; And yet could never obtain of the Pope an Establishment in that Bishoprick for some shamefull Disorders of his, of which private information was given to the Pope.</p>
            <p>Well, but you'l say, the Pope has refused to establish by his Bulls a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove five and thirty of those Bishops which are nominated by the King of <hi>France. Monsieur Talon</hi> is extreamly mistaken: For the Pope of himself refused but only two, who had both been of the Assembly of 1682. and had there Subscribed to all those Resolutions which were then taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Pope: but the rest happen'd not to be Established because those of that Assembly who were charged with Misdemeanour in the Court of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205164:8"/>
               <hi>Rome,</hi> whether by any Order from the King, or of their own accord, I know not, did absolutely declare that since these two were not admitted by his Holiness, they would not propose any more.</p>
            <p>It is not our business here to censure the carriage of that Assembly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Pope: but I think it would have become their Prudence bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not to have engaged the King their Master to make so ill a Step. Other Ministers would have used their best endeavours to have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a good Correspondence betwixt the Pope, and the King; They should have considered of the Complaints made against the nominated Bishops, and either have endeavoured to have justified them, or at least to have excused them, or to have found some means or other to have sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied his Holiness, that he might at least have accepted of those Persons which were nominated by the King; But those sweet and handsom ways of proceeding with the Pope, are with those Gentlemen, grown quite out of use. They take very different ways from these, and instead of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitating affairs, desire rather to hamper 'em more.</p>
            <p>But this is certain according to the words of the Concordat: If Briefs of nomination to any Bishoprick vacant be not within the first six Months of the vacancy presented to the Pope, his Holiness then has full Right and Absolute Power to provide and Establish what Bishops he pleases, so that instead of complaining of those so many vacant Sees in <hi>France,</hi> they should rather admire &amp; commend the Pope's Moderation, who for the good of the Christian Church, would rather in such Cases not stand upon his utmost Right, nor make use of his Absolute Power, in suddenly preferring who he pleased, as he might. Therefore if we consider the business well, 'tis to the ill Conduct of the Court of <hi>France</hi> that we must attribute those so long vacancies of Bishopricks in <hi>France;</hi> and not to any morose hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the Pope, who acts in all these things not according to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, but according to Reason, by Principles of Justice and Conscience, always ready to grant his Bulls and to confirm the nominations of the King whensoever he pleases to present such Persons as are endowed with Qualities requisite for such Employments as those. And the Pope indeed is resolved, I believe, never to promote those, that he shall find unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, notwithstanding all the instances that can be made, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing those abominable injuries of <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> who certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves in all reason in the world, to be removed from his Employment, 'till such time as he has made ample and publick satisfaction for all these Villanous Calumnies which he has so injuriously thrown upon the Pope in this Defamatory Libel of his.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> it may be will say, that the Pope refuses his Bulls
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205164:8"/>in <hi>France,</hi> because they will not believe his infallibility, nor own him Superiour to generall Councills. In this <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> is mightily mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, for t'was not only upon that account that the Pope refused his Bulls to those two Ecclesiasticks, which as were mention'd before, has been nominated by the King for Bishopricks; They know very well at <hi>Rome</hi> what the opinions of the <hi>Paris</hi> Doctors were upon this point, in the time of the Councill of <hi>Constance</hi> and of <hi>Basil,</hi> and though that opinion of theirs be rejected and disapproved by the more Orthodox men, yet they have not in that been yet expressly condemned or anathematiz'd by the Pope.</p>
            <p>Then those Ecclesiasticks had openly declared themselves against the Pope in an Assembly of Bishops (which if we believe themselves) was assembled for no other cause but to reunite the Pope and the King, and to settle a good correspondence betwixt the Clergy and the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracy of that Nation, and had yet taken upon them with the rest of that Assembly to determine, in asmuch as in them lay, the business of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galia,</hi> which yet was undoubtedly one of those great and more consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able causes which under the name of <hi>causae majores,</hi> as well by the new as by the ancient Canons, are reserved to the Sacred See, and by the express words of the Concordat; and which besides was devolved to his Holiness at that time by just and juridicall appeals. But those Ecclesiasticks then assembled were so far from joyning themselves with their head in this conjuncture to defend their own liberties, that they took all occasion they could to quarrel with the Pope their master, took upon 'em to limit his power, without any reason at all, without any necessity, and undoubtedly without any legitimate power. These were as near as I can Judge the reasons which forced the Pope to refuse his Bulls to those nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Bishops which had been in this Assembly before, and had Subscribed and approved all the decisions that then were made against the Authority of the Pope. And indeed could ever any thing be stranger in the Church of God, then to see the Bishops of a Catholick Country rise up so Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliously against their Head, a Pope so exemplar and of so holy a Life as his present Holiness is, and one that never had any quarrel with the King of <hi>France,</hi> but because he defended the Liberties of the Churches of <hi>France,</hi> and maintained the just pretensions of the Bishops of those four Conquered Provinces against the Usurpation of the <hi>Regalia,</hi> which the King of <hi>France</hi> pretended to impose where-ever he Conquered the Place. A rare occasion for those Prelates to draw up a Declaration as they did against the Ecclesiasticall power, without ever having been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered from their Provinces to treat a matter of so great importance,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205164:9"/>they themselves having been too for the most part chosen (as all the world very well knows) in the Provinciall Assemblies by violence, and by the power of the <hi>French Court,</hi> and not with that liberty of Suffrages which ought to have been. Besides it was very well known that all these points which pass'd in that Assembly were not all put to the vote, and that neither the Bishops, nor the other Deputies that were there, had the liberty to think as they pleas'd, or freely to deliver their opinions: All being concluded as the President thought fit or rather by the power and inclination of the <hi>French Court.</hi> It is not our business here to examin the four propositions of that Declaration, and the manner of their pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: That has been done already with vigour enough: and those pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chicanneries of <hi>P. Maimbourg</hi> (a fit defender of such an Assembly) have been so batter'd and broken already, that it would be to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to treat of that matter at length any more. 'Tis enough if we say, that that Assembly went farther then the Bishops of the Councill of <hi>Basil,</hi> and all the <hi>Richerists,</hi> and that they flew in the face of the Papall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with higher and far less moderation then they. The first said only, that there were some particular and extraordinary cases in which the Pope was inferiour to generall Councills: as in that of Schism, Heresie, and other insufferable disorders, but these Gentlemen of the <hi>French As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly</hi> cut off all his Authority at a Stroak, and say, that the Pope in all cases is inferiour to a generall Councill; so that according to these Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemens opinion, a Council that were legally called, and that might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently proceed to the condemning of Heresies, could not be dissolved by the Pope. If these Bishops had well perused the resolutions of that As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly in <hi>France</hi> of 1625. they would have found that their Predecessours defin'd clearly against the <hi>Richerists,</hi> and established a doctrine in the <hi>Galliean Church</hi> quite contrary to those Gentlemens late Declaration. And if they had but maturely considered the Acts reported in the Councils, they would have found the matter quite otherwise then they seem to suppose, and that indeed there is scarce any case in which the Pope is subject to a generall Councill; their Decisions and Laws being of no force, nor Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority till they are confirmed by the Sacred and Apostolick See, and by the head of the Church. This boldness and temerity of the Deputies of the Assembly, was it not enough to render 'em suspected, and to give all men good ground to think that they did not look upon the Pope as that head of the Uniuersall Church which all the Faithfull ought to obey? And such a carraige as this, so far from that profound respect which all good Catholicks owe to the Pope their Supreme Soveraign in Ecclesias<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall affairs, was it not enough to oblige his Holyness to suspend his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205164:9"/>Bulls till such time as he could be better informed of their opinions; and till they had made him some kind of satisfaction at least for so great a fault?</p>
            <p>Besides, the Pope, as I think I have told you before, offered to grant his Bulls to any other of the Kings nomination, but only such as were of that Assembly, which <hi>Mounsieur Talon</hi> has taken great care to conceal. Did not his Holiness promote to the Bishoprick of <hi>Queback</hi> in <hi>New France,</hi> the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of <hi>St. Valier</hi> upon the nomination of the most Christian King? What does the Pope do then in this behalf that is irregular? Would <hi>France</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to tye the Pope's hands more then the <hi>Concordat</hi> has done? Or do they think the Pope is oblig'd to admit all the Royall nominations with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever enquiring into the lives or capacities of the persons presented? Or would they fear violently from him that right which the <hi>Concordat</hi> gives him of refusing such as are unworthy? Or would they pretend to Judge of the Popes Judgment in this matter, and appeal to some other Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall? If the Pope has not absolute power of refusing the persons nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, why should the <hi>Concordat</hi> require as it does, that the King shall be bound to name another in three months time when ever the Pope thinks sit to refuse the first that is named? Has this Pope less Power then his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessours? Has <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> forgot what happened not Forty year a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go in the case of <hi>Monsieur de Marca,</hi> who nominated by the King for the Bishoprick of <hi>Couseraus,</hi> and afterwards for the Arch-Bishoprick of <hi>Tolose,</hi> was never able to procure the Popes Bulls, whatever instance the <hi>French</hi> Ambassadour made, till he had satisfactorily expiated those two too bold propositions of the Pope's Authority, and of the Roman Church, which were found in that famous book of his, <hi>de concordia Sacerdotii &amp; Imperii.</hi> And let not <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> tell us, that that opinion of the French Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of 1682. was formerly publickly defended in the <hi>Council of Trent</hi> by the Cardinall of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> I cannot tell whence <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> could have what he affirms; that that Cardinall had declared publickly in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, that all <hi>France</hi> was perswaded that the Pope was not infallible. For neither Father <hi>Paolo,</hi> nor Cardinall <hi>Pallavicino</hi> mention any such thing, and yet such Historians as those neither could be ignorant, nor would have dissembled a passage of that importance, without relating it to the world, and making their severall reflections upon it. It must have been therefore some instruction of the Cardinall of <hi>Lorrain</hi> given to an Agent of his in the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> called <hi>le Breton,</hi> related by <hi>Monsieur du Puy,</hi> which must have given occasion to <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> to affirm that passage so boldly as he does. But that piece, besides that 'tis much suspected to have been suppositions, or at least to have been altered and corrupted by some Enemies of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred See, it makes that Cardinall affirm that which no good Catholick
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205164:10"/>would ever at least publickly own, which is, that in <hi>France</hi> the <hi>Councill of Florence</hi> is not received. There is none but the Greek Schismaticks that reject the <hi>Councill of Florence;</hi> All the Catholicks in the world without dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty receive that Councill for Oecumenicall; and if there were any trouble, because those who adher'd to the <hi>Councill of Basil</hi> would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to the calling of the <hi>Councill of Florence,</hi> yet it is certain at last the <hi>Councill of Basil</hi> was deserted by all the Christian Princes, whereas there was not any one of the Princes of Christendom which did not admit the <hi>Councill of Florence</hi> for Oecumenicall, and submit to all it's decisions. And <hi>Monsieur Du Puy</hi> himself put's in the margent of this instruction of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> that as much of that instruction as concerns the Pope, the Sacred See, and the superiority of Councills, was never read before the Pope. Which makes it plainly appear, that though the Cardinall of <hi>Lorraine</hi> had perhaps in the heat of Contests written any such thing to his Agent, he revoked it again after having thought more seriously of it, and for that reason, it seems forbid his Agent to read it before the Pope; And besides <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> may take notice, if he please, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Lateran</hi> held under <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, in which the Pope's Authority over generall Councils was so highly Established, was received by <hi>Lewis the Twelfth,</hi> and <hi>Francis the First</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> not in their own names only, but in the name of the Nation too: And let him remember too that when <hi>Chancellour du Prat</hi> carried the Parliament a Declaration of <hi>Francis the First</hi> to justify the Advantages that <hi>France</hi> received by the <hi>Concordat,</hi> 'twas affirmed in the same Declaration, that it was certain, that the Pope was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Generall Council in all, except some very particular and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary cases. Therefore let him tell us no more, that <hi>France</hi> has always ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her'd to the Decrees of the <hi>Council of Basil</hi> in the business of the General Council's Superiority over the Pope.</p>
            <p>Let not <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> tell us neither, that all the Doctors of <hi>France</hi> are of the same opinion. We know very well how great a number there are of the best and the learnedest Men in <hi>France</hi> that condemn in their hearts the opinion of that Assembly, and are so much of a contrary opinion to theirs, that if they durst freely speak what they think, without being sent by a privy Seal from Court, to Prison or Banishment; they would stoutly oppose the Declaration of that Assembly of 1682. and would give the world good Testimony of the profound respect and submission which they bear to the Authority of the Pope, and the Decisions of the Sacred See.</p>
            <p>But whatever the particular opinions of the Divines of <hi>France</hi> may be, 'tis certain there are not many that have publickly appeared against the Authority of the Pope. And it is only to such as those that his Holiness
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:205164:10"/>refuses his Bulls, till such time as they make satisfaction for their fault; and truly had that business been handsomely manag'd; those unhappy differences which have made so great a noise in Christendom, would soon have fallen to the ground, had not those Gentlemen of the Assembly of 1682. so briskly and so Turbulently too, made that unhappy step from whence they either cannot or will not retire.</p>
            <p>Nor let <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> think to fright the Pope with threatning, that if His Holiness will not by his Bulls confirm and Establish those nominated Bishops which he thinks unworthy, <hi>France</hi> will send no more mony to <hi>Rome.</hi> Alas! this Magistrate does not know this Pope, if he think him a man that can be touch'd with so mean and base an Interest as that. The money that he Receives from <hi>France</hi> is so inconsiderable, and must when it comes be divided amongst so many, that those who are the most concerned, make very little or no account of it at all, much less will the consideration of that inconsiderable money, any ways be able to affect this Pope, whom we all know to be a man so unconcerned in all worldly things, and of so nice, and tender a Conscience, that for all the Kingdoms in the world, he could not be brought to do the least thing either contrary to his duty, or that he could think, might displease Almighty God: And yet this is one of the greatest threats of <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> to which he add's this, that the King (if his Holiness persists,) will break the <hi>Concordat.</hi> For according to the doctrine, it seems of <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> the Popes refusing to grant his Bulls to any one of those the King names, is cause sufficient for the King to break the <hi>Concordat;</hi> no more is required it seems to establish the pragmatick Sanction; but because this pragmatick practise would neither accomodate — nor the Court, and because this way the Court would be forced to use perpetuall violence in the Provinces to get those chosen which the King had a mind to, which yet would not always be affected nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> has found this expedient to abrogate and to annull at the same time, the pragmatick Sanction, and the <hi>Concordat</hi> too, and then establish a new Law which can be certainly grounded in nothing but their own vain imagination. The Election, say's <hi>Talon,</hi> of Bishops, originally belongs to the People. The people of <hi>France</hi> now are no more in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to nominate: we have some examples in the first and second rate, where Kings have nominated Bishops in some singular cases. They are the heads of their Kingdoms, and have a right to act as well in the peoples name as in their own. Therefore the King may name Bishops himself, which the Metropolitan with some other Bishops of the Diocesses, after they approved the Kings Nominations, may Consecrate and establish. This is the discourse of <hi>Monsieur Talon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:205164:11"/>
            <p> Could any man have advanced such propositions as these without first renouncing all common sence, and all the rules of Equity and Justice in the world? yet if we believe <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> he'l tell us, that this is an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent reason, that, that right which the Faithfull anciently had to appoint themselves a Bishop, since it cannot conveniently now be any more exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised in common, must necessarily pass into the person of their Soveraign the King. How can you that desire so much to be taken for the great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the liberties of the <hi>Gallican Church,</hi> abandon the pragmatick San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, grounded as well in common law, as upon the Councils of <hi>Constance</hi> and <hi>Basil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not that ordinance of <hi>Orleance</hi> worth your taking notice of, where it was decreed, that Elections of Bishops should be made by the Cathedrall Chapter, and also by Deputies of the Gentry of the Diocess, and of the principall Citizens of the Episcopall City? Why will you needs suppose that the Canonicall Elections cannot be made any more as they have been? Do you remember none of those Pleas of your Predecessours in defence of such Elections as those in their full extent? and that they look't upon 'em then, as the principall point of the Liberties of the <hi>Gallican Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not upon such maxims or principles as these that <hi>Mounsieur Talon</hi> determines any point of the matter in question; neither the liberties of Churches, nor the Ordinances of Estates, nor the Sacred Canons of the Oecumenicall Councills, which yet he uses (with so much Ostentation) to cite, are ever any rule of <hi>Monsieur Talon's</hi> opinion or carriage in this busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. The Soveraign Law which with him takes place above all Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall Laws, and those of the state besides, is a resolution to please, and comply with the Court.</p>
            <p>Settled in these resolutions and full of such extravagant designs as these, no wonder if he establish new Laws, of his own head, and by his own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Authority; He'l abolish the <hi>Concordat,</hi> because he does not like the power that the Pope has reserved to himself, of refusing such of the King's nominated Bishops, as he shall find unfit. He'l abolish the pragmatick Sanction, because the re-establishing of the ancient Elections would not suit with the present interest of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> but rather deprive the King of his right of Nomination: and therefore after having taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Pope the right of collation, he would give the King a right of nominating Bishops without being restrained by the rule of the <hi>Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat.</hi> A right, none of his Royall Predecessours ever enjoyed, but by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the <hi>Concordat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly the <hi>Church of France</hi> would be much to be blamed, if instead of being governed by the holy Canons of the Church, and Papall Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:205164:11"/>they should suffer themselves to be led away by such fancies as a lay-Judg, that dayly changes his opinion, according to the different impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions which the <hi>Court of France</hi> makes upon him; and has not of himself a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny true and Solid knowledge of the Ecclesiasticall Laws, but only takes up such Scraps as he meets with up and down in memorialls, whilest he hunts for Erudition to fill up his Plea's: nor has he either honour or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science before his eyes, nor the laws of the Church or of the State; he goes on meerly puff'd up with extravagant passion, and an Ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to please the Court.</p>
            <p>We have been forced to follow this Declaimer all this while in all his digressions; let us see now what he says of the matter in question, and of the pretended Franchises; but he makes again another great digression a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Popes Bull, <hi>in Coena Domini,</hi> then tells us, that Bull is very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, because it establishes, as he pretends, the Pope Soveraign Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of the world, and because it seems not to allow Parliaments any power to take cognizance of the possessions of Benefices, or of any causes reall or personall that belong to Ecclesiasticks.</p>
            <p>What he says of the Pope's Sovereign Authority, is of his own head, for there is no such thing in the Bull: And therefore if <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else against that Bull, but that it forbids Parliaments to meddle with Ecclesiasticall Jurisdiction, I do not see what persons in the world, though never so little equitable, can have any thing to say to it, except such Lay-Judges, as too much addicted to their own interest would bring all fish in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own Nets.</p>
            <p>But if we consider what manner <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> speaks of that Bull, we might have reason enough to think he never had read the Bull in his Life but speaks by hear-say only, and what he has learned from: other men? For first, he supposes that that Bull Establishes the Pope Sovereign Lord of the world; of which Sovereignty, there is not a word in the Bull. Secondly, he seems to suppose, that that Bull began but under <hi>Julius the Second,</hi> whereas it appears, that long before that time, other Popes as <hi>Ʋr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban the Fifth, Paul the Second,</hi> and <hi>Sixtus the Fourth,</hi> had published the like censures in their Constitutions, and many others after <hi>Judius the Second,</hi> and <hi>Paul the Third</hi> had done the same, and with the same Solemnity, which yet were never accused of being Enemies to <hi>France.</hi> Nor can I see any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> should cry down that Bull, unless it be, because it condemns Parliaments, that intrude themselves into Ecclesiasticall Affairs, and take upon 'em a jurisdiction that does not belong to them. After this Digression against the Bull, he makes a great complaint against the Pope for laying an Interdict upon the Church of St. <hi>Lewis in Rome,</hi> and as he tells us, against all the rules of Canon Law.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:205164:12"/>
            <p>'Tis not the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi>'s business, nor much less <hi>Monsieur Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>'s, to examine what the Pope does in <hi>Rome.</hi> The Pope has a Supreme Authority as well Temporal as Spiritual over that City of his, and of his Government there is to give no account, but only to God. But yet that much, I think, we may say, that they are a little more regular in their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical proceedings at <hi>Rome</hi> then in <hi>France.</hi> Would to God in <hi>France</hi> in the destruction of the Monastery of <hi>Charonne,</hi> in the dissolving the <hi>Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute</hi> of the <hi>Nuns</hi> of the <hi>Infancy,</hi> in the Elections of <hi>Ʋrbanist Abbesses,</hi> of the <hi>Cystertian Abbots,</hi> and of the <hi>Abbots</hi> of <hi>Cluny,</hi> and of the <hi>Trinitarians:</hi> In the business of the <hi>Regalia,</hi> in the Judging and Condemning of <hi>Priests,</hi> and in all other Ecclesiastical Affairs, they had but as well observed the Canons and Rules of the Church in <hi>France,</hi> as the Pope observes 'em in <hi>Rome.</hi> The Cardinal-Vicar Interdicted the Church of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> in <hi>Rome;</hi> because the Rector of the Community of Priests, which belong to that Church had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Monsieur Lavardin</hi> to Prayers, and to participation of Sacraments with them, after he had been most notoriously Excommunicated by the Pope, and in <hi>Rome</hi> it self. For what could be more notoriously publick then an Excommunication published by a Bull of the Pope in <hi>Rome,</hi> and well known both to the <hi>King of France</hi> and his Ministers, before the departure of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur Lavardin.</hi> Could he that came with Arms in his hands, and with full resolution to defend the pretended Franchises of his House in <hi>Rome,</hi> and that above five Months after the publication of this Bull, pretend ignorance then? Was not <hi>Monsieur-Lavardin</hi>'s action notorious to all the world? By what Trick or Artifice could any body excuse or dissemble the knowledge of so publick a Fact?</p>
            <p>He comes to <hi>Rome</hi> more like an Enemy, then an Ambassadour; enters the Sacred City, like a Conquered Town, he cheats the Officers of the Customs at the Gates, brings in his Ammunition of War, the Palace of Cardinal <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesius</hi> is filled with strong Guards and Troups of Armed men, they go the round about the Palace in a Military manner all night, as if they had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made a Cittadel in <hi>Rome;</hi> And that all this might be the more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely known to the City, these Guards are relieved, and these Rounds are made at the sound of a Bell. After all this, would those of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> pretend to doubt whether <hi>Monsieur Lavardin</hi> had incurr'd the Popes Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion published by a Bull? And if these Facts were so notorious that they could neither be disowned nor excused, how could the Rector of the Priests of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> admit <hi>Monsieur Lavardin</hi> in time of Divine Service to Church, and to the participation of the Sacraments, without pulling upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the Censure of the Church?</p>
            <p>But <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> replies, <hi>The Excommunication was not denounced.</hi> Has
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205164:12"/>this Magistrate forgot that Article of the pragmatick Sanction, and of the Concordat too, where it's said in express terms, that <hi>to incurr Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or Interdict by Communicating in Holy things with a Person that has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriously incurr'd the Excommunication, it is not at all necessary that there should be any precedent denunciation.</hi> 'Twas a thing notorious that <hi>Monsieur Lavar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din</hi> had incurr'd the Excommunication expressed in the Bull: First, because the Bull it self was notorious: Secondly, because he publickly and constant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made a defence against it, when he made that open and Military defence at the Palace where he Lodg'd, of his pretended Franchises: the Rector and Priests of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> could not be ignorant of all this, and yet they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly gave him the Sacraments; did not they very well deserve then to have their Church Interdicted, since it was a fault committed not by any one particular Person but by the whole Community? And therefore let not <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> bring all those common places against Interdicts in this case. The question is not here of the Interdict of a Kingdom or Province, which were formerly so much in use, but our Question is of an Interdict only of one Parochial Church, and that in <hi>Rome,</hi> over which the Pope has all Absolute Jurisdiction; and the Interdict is founded upon the disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of a whole Community. Nor can <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> with all his Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks bring any solid Argument against it. But the Pope cannot Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate an Ambassador, says he, nor a Magistrate acquitting himself of his duty and executing the orders of the King his Master. 'Tis Evident (have as ill Principles of Religion as you will) you cannot but own the Pope has an Absolute Universall Power without exception, without limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or restriction, to bind, and release all, or any Christians whatsoever. <hi>Quaecunque Ligaveris,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And upon what ground that unheard of Priviledge is founded, that Ambassadors and Magistrates (if they be Christians) cannot be Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated by the Pope, I cannot find: undoubtedly they as well as other Men, are Subject to the Keys of Sr. <hi>Peter,</hi> and to the Authority of the Church: Nor do I see why they may not in executing the orders of their Masters, fall into such Crimes as may pull upon 'em the Censures of the Church.</p>
            <p>May an Ambassadour, do you think, by order of his master, have a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Assassinated without incurring excommunication? and to speak more particularly of the matter in question, shall an Ambssadour by order of his Master invade the Patrimony of Sr. <hi>Peters,</hi> affront the head of the Church in <hi>Rome</hi> it self, take from the Pope in a part of his Capitall City, the power of exercising his Soveraign Authority without incurring excommunication, and those other penalties the Canons have provided against those Sacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205164:13"/>Persons that steal holy things, and usurp the endowments of the Church? This is a new Divinity which Christendom has not heard of yet. 'Tis easy enough to make appear not only by the Canons and by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of the universall Church, but also by the Canons of the Church of <hi>France,</hi> that Kings themselves may be excommunicated, much more their Ambassadours, who certainly are not priviledged more then their Masters. The Ecclesiasticall history furnishes us with abundance of examples of <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>German</hi> Emperours, of Kings of <hi>France</hi> and of <hi>England,</hi> that have felt and acknowledg'd the weight of excommunication. <hi>Clotaire, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the first, <hi>Philip August,</hi> the examples of <hi>Henry the third,</hi> and <hi>Henry the fourth</hi> are too publick in <hi>France,</hi> and too well remembred to be denyed.</p>
            <p>The greatest Enemies the Sacred See has in the world, agree, that at the beginning of the Eighth age, <hi>Gregory the second</hi> excommunicated <hi>Leo Ironomatus,</hi> and this Heretick Emperour lost by that means the <hi>Exarcat</hi> of <hi>Ravenna.</hi> All the defenders of the <hi>Gallican</hi> rights agree, that three of the French Kings, <hi>Clotaire, Philip the First,</hi> and <hi>Philip August,</hi> were all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by Popes, and were obliged every one to put away their Concubines, and to receive again their lawfull wifes which they had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled. <hi>Nicholas the First</hi> excommunicated <hi>Lothaire,</hi> for having put away <hi>Fewburg</hi> his wife, and marrying <hi>Valdrade</hi> his Concubine. <hi>Ʋrban the Second</hi> excommunicated <hi>Phillip the First</hi> in the Councill of <hi>Clermont.</hi> And <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent the Third</hi> excommunicated <hi>Philip August</hi> upon the like account: so that none of all his Subjects durst have any access to him till he had received his wife, and abandoned his Concubine. And all that while they dated in <hi>France, Regnante Christo,</hi> without taking any notice of <hi>Philip August</hi> at all: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr the Reader to Father <hi>Maimbourg,</hi> that great enemy to Popes, for the Stories of the Emperours <hi>Henry the Fourth, Henry the First, Frederick the First, Philip the First, Othon the Fourth, Frederick the Second, Conrade the First, Raymond Earl of Tolose</hi> Excommunicated by <hi>Alexander the Third;</hi> and of a great number of Kings of <hi>England</hi> Excommunicated, by Popes, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were absolved, did ask upon their knees absolution from the Excommunication incurr'd, either before the Popes, or before their Legates. We find besides that, <hi>Foulques Arch-Bishop of Rheims</hi> threatned to Excommunicate <hi>Charles the Simple</hi> if he made Allyance with <hi>Normans,</hi> who were then Heathens, by a Letter penn'd thus: <hi>Sciatis quod si hoc fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritis, &amp; consiliis nostris non acquieveritis, nunquam me fidelem habebitis, sed &amp; quoscunque potero a vestra fidelitate revocabo, &amp; cum omnibus co-Episcopis meis vos &amp; omnes vestros Excommunicationis perpetuo anathemate condemnabo.</hi> And in the Sixth Book of the <hi>Capitulers,</hi> ch. 249. 'tis said expressly, <hi>Hujus Constitutionis forma servetur ut execrandum anathema fiat, ut velut Prevaricator
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205164:13"/>Catholicae fidei, semper a domino Reus existat quicunque Regum deinceps Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonis hujus censuram in quocunque crediderit esse violandam.</hi> This may be seen in the Capitulers approv'd and authorized by the Kings of <hi>France;</hi> And those Kings all acknowledged the power of the Church, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly submitted to its Authority. They openly detested their faults ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by themselves or by their Ambassadours. They earnestly begg'd Absolution of the Popes. They faithfully executed the Penances which were enjoined them for Satisfaction for their faults, and for reparation of the Scandal which they by their ill example had given to the world. But if those Princes had had for their Counsel <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> they would have lookt upon the Vatican Thunder but <hi>like Squibs that expire but in Smoke, and hurt no body more then those that throw them;</hi> they would learn to have forced the Priests by severe Imprisonments or by seizures of their Estates to have opened them the Doors of the Churches, and to have given them the Sacraments, they would have railed at the Pope, wounded their Fame and torn their Reputations, as this Orator does, without any ground in the world. They woul'd have appeal'd from the Pope to their Parliaments, and have complained of the abuses, or to the next General Council that shall be called. But those innocent Monarchs and Emperours did no such thing; but with a sincere and Christian Devotion acknowledg'd, that as they were as capable of Sin as other men were, so though Emperours; yet as well as other men, they might incurr the Censures of the Church; They placed their greatness and Glory not in contesting the Pope's Authority by pitifull Chicanneries and tricks of the Law, but in submitting with humility to the Laws of the Church, in mending their faults and excesses: in giving good example to their People, and in teaching their People by the practice of the Prince, in what awe of the Ecclesiastical Censures all good Christians ought to be, what deference and respect they ought to pay to the Church and to him that is President there, the visible Head and Vicar of <hi>Christ.</hi> Thus much indeed we must confess, that some Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of <hi>France</hi> jealous of their Authority pretended, yet afore, that the Censuring and Excommunicating of Kings when they deserved it, belonged properly to the Bishops of the Country, where those Kings Reigned, rather then to the Pope; perhaps they might think some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there might be danger in delay, or for several other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons whatever it was; in that Sense certainly and no other, those Bishops of <hi>France</hi> must have formerly written those shamefull and temeratious words to Pope <hi>Gregory the Fourth: If you come hither to Excommunicate our King, you shall return excommunicated
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205164:14"/>your self.</hi> Words which the Bishops of <hi>France</hi> may well blush at for their Predecessours sake, and fitter to be buried in eternall oblivion, then to be interpreted as they are by <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> for the advantage of the present times. What? The Pope shall return excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? By whom? By the Bishops of <hi>France?</hi> If a Pope can be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by particular Bishops, then the Pope is not only subject to generall Councills, as <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> pretends to have it, but to the particular Bishops of <hi>France</hi> too, whensoever they shall be in an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to oppose him. These are arguments of that extravagance that they destroy themselves fast enough, and need no other refutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But all that can in any rationall sence be made of those words of the <hi>French</hi> Bishops to <hi>Gregory the Fourth,</hi> is, that the <hi>French</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops did believe themselves to have power enough then to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate their Kings without complaining farther to the Pope.</p>
            <p>Now because of the great inconveniences that might follow by the particular Bishops having so great a power as to excommunicate Kings, as authorizing Factions and fomenting Rebellions in severall nations might be, therefore the Christian Kings earnestly always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired not to be excommunicated but by Popes; And if <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> had taken the pains to read over the Bulls of Pope <hi>Clement the Sixth</hi> and other Popes granted at the earnest request of Severall Kings, he might have seen there that the Popes and Kings did both agree of that power which Popes still have to excommunicate Kings for those faults that fall under the censures of the Church, and that the Kings then, only desired to be exempted from any censure such Bishops as were their own subjects might throw upon them, because of ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences that might follow as I have observed before.</p>
            <p>Let him but read the instructions of <hi>Charles the Ninth</hi> given to his Ambassadours who were with Pope <hi>Paul the Fourth,</hi> about the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Navar,</hi> the supplications of <hi>Augennet</hi> Bishop of <hi>Maus</hi> in the name of <hi>Henry the Third,</hi> and those of Cardinall <hi>D'ossat</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> in behalf of <hi>Henry the Fourth:</hi> And see what sincere Submissions and Acknowledgments those Bishops and Cardinalls made in behalf of those Kings, how humbly they Submitted to the Censures of the Church, how clearly and heartily they desired to be absolved. The Judges and Advocates of the last age although the greatest part of them were infected with those hereticall Maxims which then were so spread through this Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> yet all agree of this truth, and Acknowledge that <hi>Theodosius, Leon,</hi> the two <hi>Fredericks,</hi> and other Emperours were excommunicated, and that Popes used the same power
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205164:14"/>over the Kings of <hi>France.</hi> I know those Lawyers might be perhaps of opinion then, that the Pope could not throw an Interdict upon a whole Nation, or abandon it to the next occupant: But that is not our question here; our present question is only, whether Kings or their Ambassadours may be Excommunicated by the Pope when they commit crimes that fall under the censures of the Church? I affirm that they can; and say no man can deny that, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the supreme Authority of the Church, which depends nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of time, nor place, nor of the capriciousness of men, but stands settled and unshaken upon that Rock of Life, <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> and upon his Sacred word, against which Hell it self shall not be able to prevail.</p>
            <p>By what we have said it clearly appears that Kings may be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, and their Ambassadors in Executing the Orders of their Masters (if they be Catholicks) may incurr Excommunication too, if in Executing those Orders of their Masters, they commit such crimes as fall under the censures of the Church.</p>
            <p>I shall not here make it my business to refute those falsities which <hi>Mensieur Talon</hi> alledges concerning what pass'd at <hi>Naples,</hi> occasion'd by some Ecclesiastical Censures which the <hi>Nuncio</hi> there had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced against some Counsellors and other Officers of the Council of State. For that business was so certainly and publickly known, that not one of all those who were then Excommunicated by the <hi>Nuncio</hi> there, ever durst appear at any Divine Service in any Church. And therefore to be able to keep their <hi>Christmas</hi> last past; like true Children of the Church, they humbly demanded Absolution, which was granted 'em with the clause <hi>de reincidentia,</hi> that is, in case of relapse to be in force, if afterwards they should not fully submit to perform all that was enjoyned 'em: And all the world knows as well what passed some years ago in the Kingdom of <hi>Sicily;</hi> where the <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> and some other Officers of the King were Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by the <hi>Arch-Bishop</hi> of <hi>Palermo,</hi> for something they had done against the Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction. Where the Offenders were all forced to appear before the same <hi>Arch-Bishop,</hi> and receive of him publickly Absolution in the ordinary form. Nor need I take much notice of those little Chicanneries which <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> delivers with such an air that we may see, he himself does not value 'em much; As that the Bull was not published in <hi>France,</hi> nor signified to <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur Lavardin.</hi> But the Bull was affixt and publisht at <hi>Rome,</hi> which was enough to be sufficiently known to those that live there.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:205164:15"/>
            <p> Nor is it our question whither <hi>Monsieur de Lavardin</hi> having not presented his Letters of Credence, and having not yet been acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the Pope, were Ambassadour or not. But if that were the question, we can easily make it appear by the Laws of Nations, that to be an absolute Ambassadour, 'tis not enough to be sent in that quality by any Prince; but he must be admitted, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the Sovereign Prince, to whom he is sent, before he can be truly stiled an Ambassadour: whence it happened formerly, that when any Pope sent a <hi>Nuncio</hi> to <hi>France</hi> that the King did not like, he was always stop'd upon the Frontiers, and never acknowledged for <hi>Nuncio</hi> at all.</p>
            <p>All that we have to make out, is, that whether <hi>Monsieur de Lavardin</hi> were Ambassadour, or whether he vere not, he either did know, or ought to have known, being in <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Pope had forbid, under pain of Excommunication. to be incurr'd by the very Fact whenever it should be committed, to pretend to attribute any such Priviledge of Franchises to any particular House or Quarter in the City of <hi>Rome. Monsieur de Lavardin</hi> did attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to himself and his place of Residence in <hi>Rome,</hi> that pretended right of Franchise publiquely and constantly. He has no Priviledge that can shelter him from the Censures of the Church, nay, the King his Master has none for his own Royal Person: he did therefore certainly incurr the Excommunication declared in the Pope's Bull, nor could without trampling on the power of the Pope, and treading the Authority of the Christian Church under foot, enter, as he did, into the Parish Church of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> and receive the Blessed Sacrament before he had received Absolution from the Pope. <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur Talon</hi> after having confidently without any proof imposed upon us this Proposition; that an Ambassadour cannot be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by the Pope; defends in particular, that the Pope cannot at least Excommunicate him upon the account of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Franchises which are in question; Because, says <hi>Talon,</hi> those Franchises are things purely Temporal, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not properly be the Subject of an Excommunication; And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, because the King has been in possession of that right time out of mind.</p>
            <p>But before I dive further into the business, I'le first ask <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur Talon,</hi> what right the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> has to meddle with, or enquire into the Franchises of <hi>Rome?</hi> Can that belong to their Jurisdiction, or which way is it within their reach? The <hi>Kings
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:205164:15"/>of France</hi> have always limited that Company of Persons assembled in the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> to take Cognizance only betwixt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Party of their own Dominions: But has any King ever given 'em power to Judge of difficulties that may happen, or Causes that may depend betwixt them and the Pope? Nay which way could any King or his present Majesty give 'em any such Power?</p>
            <p>But to examine the business to the bottom, we must see first what the Pretensions of the Ambassadours of <hi>France</hi> are in the City of <hi>Rome?</hi> and then upon what they are grounded.</p>
            <p>If we believe <hi>Monsieur Talon,</hi> the <hi>King of France</hi> might pretend to be Sovereign <hi>Prince of Rome;</hi> and turn out the Pope. A new and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of right that neither <hi>Pithon,</hi> nor <hi>Du Puy</hi> ever yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood or offered to mention in that Collection which they have made of rights which <hi>France</hi> has in other Princes Dominions in all parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> and yet <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> confidently tells us, that the <hi>King of France</hi> at present has favoured the Pope upon this account, by pretending no farther then he does to the Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chises with a reserve of right to be renewed some other time, when the King pleases, or upon the first Quarrel the King may have with the Pope. But at present <hi>Monsieur Tolon</hi> will go no further, then to defend that the <hi>King of France</hi> has a Right of <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> to make the Lodgings or House where he dwells, a Priviledged place, that is, that his Ambassadour may Establish him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self there in what Quality or Condition he pleases: For the Palace of <hi>Farnesius</hi> where he resides, being but a borrowed house, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Duke of Parma:</hi> he yet, besides the profits which his Servants make of it to several persons that Establish themselves there, pretends to make an <hi>Asylum</hi> and safe retreat of it for all <hi>Bandits, Assassinates, Poysoners, Thieves, Atheists, Sacrilegious Persons,</hi> for all <hi>Debauched Women,</hi> even those who run from their Husbands, and for all sorts of <hi>Villains</hi> whatsoever.</p>
            <p>He pretends, that neither the Justice of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor Officers, can take any Criminal from thence, or Prosecute any that are there: That the Ambassadour there has power, and those that are with him, to fight and kill any that shall (though with the Popes Authority) pursue a Criminal thither, nor that they are any ways obliged to deliver those Offenders into the hands of Justice at all. And this <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> maintains to be an unalienable right of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> from which that King will never depart, and which Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of <hi>Paris</hi> has desired him to maintain.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:205164:16"/>
            <p> At this indeed the Christian World might be sufficiently allarm'd; And is undoubtedly very much surprised to see, that Magistrates so enlighten'd as those Gentlemen of the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> pretend to be; should ever in the face of the Christian World presume to defend and maintain a pretension so highly unjust as that of the <hi>Franchises</hi> in <hi>Rome:</hi> and it is as hard for us to understand how all those persons that were consulted in that case, could be so blinded; how they could come to lose all the use of Reason they had, how they could so oppose common sence, as to confound that ridiculous pretension of <hi>France,</hi> so contrary to all Laws Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and Divine, with the Law of Nations as they do, and that crudely too, without any qualification or limitation at all. If the <hi>King of France</hi> had pretended to have had some particular Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty in <hi>Rome,</hi> or some Territory, some part of <hi>Rome</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with a Right to Judge Criminals that might be taken there, and determine such causes as might be brought thither; such a right as this, (though the most ridiculous in the World, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the least appearance of Justice, (yet in this respect) would be more supportable then that other of the Franchises, because in such a Right or Jurisdiction as this, Criminals at least would not be sheltered, but at some rate or other might be brought to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dign Punishment, though by different Lords, yet in all parts of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is a Right which the <hi>French Ambassadour</hi> has not yet thought of, though we have reason enough to believe that the <hi>King of France</hi> does not want, neither in his Court, nor in his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no, nor in his Counsel of Conscience neither, those that would be ready enough to set up this Extravagant Pretension too, if they found the King were but inclined to it; They would tell him that <hi>Charlemain</hi> and other of his Predecessors, Kings of <hi>France,</hi> having Established that Sovereignty of the Pope in <hi>Rome,</hi> the least thing this Great Prince their Successor can pretend to, would be modestly to divide that Sovereignty with the Pope, and especially, if his Majesty were so moderate as to limite that Sovereignty to the Quarters only of Ambassadors aboad in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> does not drive so far as this: but only maintains, that although the <hi>King of France</hi> has no kind of Sovereignty in <hi>Rome,</hi> yet from the very moment that a Criminal goes into the <hi>French</hi> Ambassadors Quarters, which Quarters of his comprehend ample Squares, a great circuit of Streets, and Houses, yet whatever
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:205164:16"/>Crime it is that he has committed, he can be no further pursued by any Justice in <hi>Rome,</hi> nay, without ever being Tryed or Judged, without ever being Pardoned, his crime is absolutely extinguished, and he absolved from the very moment that he sets his Foot upon the Territory of the Ambassador of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But pray, let us put the case that other Ambassadors did pretend to the same right of Franchises in <hi>Rome</hi> as <hi>Monsieur Lavardin</hi> does (and certainly they might as well as he) if they all Entred <hi>Rome</hi> in Triumph; if every one kept Garrison in their own Quarters as <hi>Monsieur Lavardin</hi> did, to defend their pretended Franchises. A <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditt</hi> that should Assassinate one of <hi>Monsieur Lavardins</hi> Train, or a Notable Thief that should get an opportunity to run away with his Cupboard of Plate, such a Murtherer or Thief would have no more to do then to run to another Ambassadors with his Booty, and both Thief and Murtherer would be clear of their crimes: I hardly believe <hi>Monsieur Lavardin,</hi> as Zealous as he is now for that right of his Masters, would then be so unconcerned in his own, as to think that his Master then or any Prince else could have any right at all to such Mischievous Priviledges, as such a protection of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers and Thieves. Then under the smart of his own losses, his Eyes would be so opened, he would think the Franchises the most insupportable grievance in the World, and finde his great Master out, some better things to protext, then Crimes, and some better sort of men to favour then Murtherers and Thieves, and would be easily brought to conceive that these pretended Franchises were truly as much; and with as great reason to be abolish'd as some of those obsolete rights of some particular Lordships in <hi>France,</hi> which were with reason destroyed because they were contrary to good Morality, to the Law of Nature, and Nations too.</p>
            <p>And yet this is that specious Right which <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> pretends to maintain. And if we should ask him what he grounds it upon: since he finds nothing like it neither in his own Memorials, nor those of the Court neither, he is feign to draw his foundations into a Narrow compass; and therefore tell us only of Three Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours that have been in possession of that right, and of an Article of Treaty made at <hi>Pisa,</hi> betwixt Pope <hi>Alexander the Seventh,</hi> and the King of <hi>France</hi> that now is, which says nothing less, nay, which indeed says quite contrary to what they would have it say. But we must follow <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> close in the narrow compass he has taken of grounds to find out the bottom of these pretensions.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:205164:17"/>
            <p> To settle the grounds of this Priviledge therefore, First, I ask <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> whether he owns the Pope for Sovereign Prince in <hi>Rome,</hi> or if he dare contest the Sovereignty with him? He dares not contest it, and if he did, we are able to make appear that this Sovereignty has been Established and owned many Ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Race, from whence the present <hi>King of France</hi> came, and had possession of the Throne.</p>
            <p>Now if the Pope be Sovereign Lord of the Ecclesiastical State, with the highest Sovereignty, as much as any Crowned Head what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, without holding either of the Emperour, or any other Crown, we must examine and see how the present <hi>King of France</hi> can come to pretend to any right in the middle of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Capital City of the Ecclesiastical State.</p>
            <p>This is a thing most undeniable, nay, even amongst the Civil Lawyers of <hi>France</hi> themselves, that the Right of Sovereignty is imprescriptible: So <hi>Monsieur le Bret</hi> Advocate General, speaks of it in his Treaty of Sovereignty, where he clearly demonstrates that the Right of Sovereignty is inviolable, and that the <hi>Centinary</hi> possession, as they call it, or the enjoyment for many Ages can make no prescription against Sovereignty. Now since the power of Life and Death, and of punishing the guilty, is as <hi>Monsieur le Bret</hi> observes too very well, the most important power that any Sovereign has: The Pope being Sovereign Lord in <hi>Rome</hi> with the highest Sovereignty that can be, and owned for such by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Princes sufficiently in that great respect they pay the Pope by their Ambassadours giving place to his <hi>Nuncio's</hi> wherever they meet. It follows necessarily that the Pope has an Absolute and undeniable right to apprehend and chastice the guilty, throughout the whole extent of the Ecclesiastical State, especially in <hi>Rome</hi> the Capital City, and consequently that the pretended possession of the Ambassadour of <hi>France</hi> is but a meer Usurpation, and that but of short time, which of whatever continuance it were, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own Civilian's Opinion, can never prescribe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Absolute, and so long Established Sovereignty of the Pope. Now let <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> consider with himself how he Pleads for his own Sovereign the <hi>King of France,</hi> and whether he does not defend the right of his Sovereignty to be imprescriptible and inalienable; and then pray let him tell us in how different a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance he weighs Sovereignty, when he pleads against <hi>Rome,</hi> and the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty of the Pope; yet Absolute Sovereignty certainly is, or ought
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205164:17"/>to be every where the same. How would they treat the Pope's <hi>Nuncio</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> if he should once pretend to such Franchises as <hi>Monsieur Lavardin</hi> does in <hi>Rome?</hi> yet Soveraign Rights are recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call so far that as one Soveraign uses another, so the other ought to use him; And since the Law of Nations ought to be the rule of the Priviledges which belong to Ambassadours in Generall; the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadour of <hi>France</hi> can pretend to no more priviledge in <hi>Rome</hi> then the <hi>Nuncio</hi> of the Pope may pretend to at <hi>Paris. Monsieur Talon</hi> would do well to consult upon this point, <hi>Grotius de Jure belli ac pacis,</hi> and then perhaps he may frame a more reasonable idea, and truer, of the Priviledges and Immunities of Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, then he made of his own head, when he first undertook to defend the Usurpation of the Ambassadour of <hi>France.</hi> Since it is therefore clear, that the Pope being an absolute Sovereign, and a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign that holds not of any, and does homage to none, and that has so absolute a Sovereign Power, that neither suffers attaint, nor is prescriptible: The power of apprehending and punishing Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, which is the importantest part of his Sovereign Power, ought to be also imprescriptible. And therefore <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> must first destroy the absolute Sovereignty of the Pope, before he can rob him of the right of apprehending and punishing Criminalls in any part of <hi>Rome,</hi> or from taking them from the houses of Ambassadours themselves; much less should he abuse the Officers of the Pope that come to execute his Justice there.</p>
            <p>But now let us see more in particular upon what <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> grounds his pretended priviledge of Franchises in <hi>Rome:</hi> Either he defends it as a right-inseparable from any Ambassadour in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, or else a right attach'd particularly to the Ambassadours of <hi>France.</hi> Again, either he pretends to that right in all the Courts of Christendom where the <hi>French</hi> Ambassadours come, or else only in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and there as belonging only to the <hi>French</hi> Ambassadour too, and no other. And then it may be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, that in <hi>Rome</hi> only he pretends, because that it is an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall State, where the Sovereign has neither the will, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the power to resist the formidable power of the most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian King. Finally, whether he pretends to this right by privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or by concession of Popes; whither he pretends to it by Title in Fee, or Conquests, or by <hi>Transactions</hi> and <hi>Concordat,</hi> or else meerly by a possession that the <hi>French</hi> Ambassadours have had
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205164:18"/>of this pretended right for about twenty years; <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> does not tell us on which of all these he grounds his Title.</p>
            <p>If it be upon the bare title of Ambassador, as Ambassador, and no more, then all Ambassadours ought to have that same priviledge in all Courts. Yet <hi>France,</hi> 'tis thought would hardly be brought to yield to such a priviledge as that, though all other States did.</p>
            <p>But if it be meerly upon the account and right of the Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of <hi>France,</hi> and a right that he dares pretend to neither in no place but <hi>Rome,</hi> we may with reason enough ask him, upon what he grounds his Chimericall pretensions? He can make out no Title at all. For first, there's no <hi>Concordat</hi> or Transaction made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Pope and King of any such thing. There is not any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that bears it. The Kings of <hi>France</hi> never Conquered the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor none ever gave it the Pope upon that Condition. We say nothing of the Treaty of <hi>Pisa,</hi> because <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self speaks but a word of it passing, and lets us sufficiently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand that he dares not himself rely upon so ruinous a Foundation as that; for the question was not then of the Franchises which we dispute of now, but there having been some Insolencies committed by the <hi>Corsers,</hi> the business was how to provide for the security of the Ambassadour's House and Family for the future: which was then promised. But this was only to secure the Ambassadour and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, there was no mention of Franchises, such as are now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to. What was the securing of the Ambassadour's Family and himself, to the securing of <hi>Banditts</hi> and all sorts of Criminals? To which I may safely add, and can prove it by Writings, that there was indeed then some mention made of endowing the place or Square before the Palace of <hi>Farnesius</hi> with the Priviledge of Franchise, but the Pope that then was, <hi>Alexander the Seventh,</hi> absolutely refused to grant any such thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> then at last is reduced, in the proofs of his Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chises, barely to the Possession or rather Usurpation of three Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadours, of which we deny that two of the three were ever in the absolute Possession of any such thing. The first manifest Usurpation therefore of that right of Franchises has been but since the time of the Duke <hi>D'Estrée.</hi> 'Tis very well known how in the time of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Tenth</hi> to vex that Pope, and his Principal Ministers, all For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Ambassadours that were then in <hi>Rome,</hi> were induced and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged violently to make themselves Masters of their Quarters, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205164:18"/>take possession: But this violent possession which they took then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to so many Bulls, and in despight of the Pope's resistance, can that ground a prescription against an Absolute Sovereign in his own Dominions? And though forced by the exigence perhaps of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent times, or for other reasons best known to himself, that Usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation was endured or rather dissembled for a time: Must the Pope never therefore defend the Rights of his Sovereignty? How many Rights and pretensions to Rights has the <hi>King of France</hi> set up that his Predecessours never thought of?</p>
            <p>But that which is most remarkable in this business, is, that though our Lord the Pope knew very well, that there was no abuse in the City of <hi>Rome</hi> that made more noise then this did, nor that had more need of a Remedy, yet he would not do it hastily, nor with a high hand, but with all the sweetness that might be, and as insensibly as he could. The Pope represented it to the King either at the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or at the death of the Ambassadours concerned; and with so much Prudence it was carried, that no Officers of Justice ever appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red about the Palace of <hi>Farnesius,</hi> not only while the Duke <hi>D'Estree</hi> was there, but not as long as his Body lay in the House, which is a most evident sign that the Pope did not publish his Bull against the pretended Franchises on purpose to affront the <hi>King of France,</hi> but rather out of a motive of Justice, for the security of the Publick, and for the quiet of his Capital City, by taking from Criminalls all hopes of impunity by such Priviledge as the <hi>French</hi> now pretend to in so considerable a part of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> as all that belongs to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Farnesius</hi> is. Nor yet did the Pope come to the publication of those Bulls, 'till he had long and to no purpose made many earnest Addresses by his <hi>Nuncio</hi> to obtain of the <hi>King of France</hi> that his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadours might depart from that unreasonable pretence of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of Franchise in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus his Holiness carried himself in the publication of his Bull, and yet chiefly for Publishing that Bull, <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> calls the Pope Enemy to <hi>France— Opiniatre,</hi> Friend to all that oppose <hi>France,</hi> Supporters of Hereticks, especially the <hi>Jansenists</hi> and <hi>Quietists.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which indeed is to be wonder'd at more then all, is, that whilst the King of <hi>France</hi> professes so great a zeal for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as so effectively to reduce all the Dissenters of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the bosom of the Church, his Officers in the mean while use their utmost endeavours to asperse the head of the Church,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205164:19"/>and to obscure the glorious reputation of the Sacred See. And this perhaps is a thing as strange as that, and which after ages will hardly believe, that the Magistrates and Officers of a King who Governs with such Justice and Authority in his own Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, should strive to tear from an Absolute Sovereign the Pope, in the middle of <hi>Rome,</hi> a power to erect under pretence of Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chises, an <hi>Asylum</hi> for all sorts of Villany, against all Right, or without any ground in the World. 'Twould better have become so great and so Christian a King as his Majesty of <hi>France,</hi> to have employed his power to have supported so good a Pope as this, and one that has done so much for the Exaltation of the Christian name; to have seconded his Piety, to have strengthen'd his Holy intentions; and to have maintained the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in that Authority and splendor which was given it by God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> at last pretends, that the question betwixt King and Pope, being of Franchises of Quarters only, was a thing meerly Temporal; and therefore since the Pope cannot be Judge in his own cause, he could not Publish a Bull of Excommunication against those that should establish the Franchises; the most he could offer at, would be to forbid it under pain of High Treason as his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessours had done.</p>
            <p>Perhaps if there were now that respect had to the Majesty of Sovereignty, which formerly has been, or to the Head of the Church, either, it may be that the setting up of those pretended Privileges would have been forbidden only under pain of High Treason, and no more.</p>
            <p>But at present things are in that Condition in Christendom, that his Holiness thought it necessary to employ all the Strength and Authority of the Christian Church, to stop so Scandalous a disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as that, and yet that cannot do, neither. For to our great grief, we see that the Churches Authority with all her severest censures is now trod under foot, and Catholicks themselves speak as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptibly of 'em, as the worst part of <hi>Calvinists</hi> do, nor are Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of Justice and Religion sufficient to prevail with those men, who have engaged his Majesty of <hi>France</hi> in this indefensible and scandalous point now in question.</p>
            <p>But let us go on to satisfy <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> in his other difficulties. I say therefore, the Pope does not appear Judge in his own cause, by publishing his Bull, any more then the <hi>King of France</hi> is his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205164:19"/>own Judge by publishing his Declaration in such things as regard the Government of his own Dominions, nor is he any more Judge there in his own cause then the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> is, when they maintain their own Jurisdiction: The Pope as Sovereign makes a Bull for the Government of <hi>Rome,</hi> to maintain Order and Justice there; This Bull is executed but only in the Pope's Dominions, and therefore it neither was, nor is necessary to be signified in <hi>France,</hi> nor to <hi>Monsieur Lavardin;</hi> nor was published there any more then the Edicts of the <hi>King of France,</hi> are published out of <hi>France,</hi> or signified to any Ambassadors. And yet those Edicts in <hi>France</hi> are Executed without contradiction, or without any bodies complaining that the <hi>King of France</hi> is Judge in his own cause.</p>
            <p>But we see very well what they aim at in <hi>France,</hi> they would have the Pope lookt upon in regard of Kings, only as a Lord of the Fee, or as a Vassal in regard of his Sovereign. But they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely mistaken, for both the Spiritual and Temporal Power of the Pope are independant of all the Kings and Emperours that are upon the Earth: he holds both his Powers immediately of God. And therefore if Kings and other Princes with so great obstinacy defend their Pretensions, and those sometimes ill enough grounded too, why should not the Pope with as great resolution defend and preserve that both Spiritual and Temporal Authority which God hath put in his hands? And though perhaps he may not make use of those Temporal Arms which he has, or might have, if he pleases to repell the violence of those infamous Calumnies and insults with which they attack him: yet he has other ways of defending those rights with which God has entrusted him, which amongst good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians ought to be more formidable then Temporal Arms: the Prayers which he pours forth before God, the Sacrifice he offers, and the Tears which he sheds to beg the Protection of that God, whose Vicar he is, and in whom only he trusts; under the omnipotent hand of which God, the most powerfull Kings ought to tremble, especially those who take upon 'em to attack the Saints, and Vicars of Christ, <hi>Timeat orationem, qui non timuit exhortationem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But still <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> maintains that no person whatsoever can be Excommunicated for Temporal things. I answer him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to that point, that the Pope does not Excommunicate for Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral things, but for Enormous Sins, and for the Crimes that are occasioned by Temporal things: As for Example, nothing can be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:205164:20"/>more Temporal then Silver and Gold, and yet the Canons of <hi>France</hi> as well as those of the Universal Church Excommunicate those Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Thieves who steal Silver or Gold out of the Churches.</p>
            <p>But pray reflect a little; do not the Parliaments of <hi>France</hi> oblige the Officials sometimes by Vertue of the New Codex, to give their Monitory Letters, and in pursuance to fulminate their Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations for things meerly Temporal? So, though the question of the Ambassadours Quarters in <hi>Rome,</hi> were a business meerly Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, yet the Crime they commit in attributing to those Quarters of theirs a Franchise of that Mischievous Nature, so unjustly as they do, may justly be punished with Excommunication. But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this I think must pass with our Adversaries themselves for certain enough; that the Usurpation of any thing that belongs to the Church, is an Enormous Crime, and a Sacrilege that deserves to be punished with Excommunication: The Canons made in those Ancient Councils of <hi>France,</hi> which <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> affirms to have been called by the only Authority of Kings, and the Capitulars of <hi>Charlemain,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the bould, Pronounce <hi>Anathema's</hi> against all those that Invade, that Plunder or Usurp the Tyths or any Rights, Lands, Rents, or Jurisdictions belonging to the Church. These Councils and Capitulers both, put all sorts of Goods, Rights, and Jurisdictions belonging to the Church all in the same rank of things that are Consecrated to God, and of which consequently the Usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation must be a Sacrilege that deserves to be struck with <hi>Anathema:</hi> and if the least Lordships or Jurisdictions that belong to Bishops or Abbots, are all received for the Holy things according to the Holy Canons; who can deny that the right of Sovereignty in <hi>Rome,</hi> which so many Ages with the consent and applauses of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom, has ever belonged to the Sacred See, is a thing so Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred that it cannot be violently torn from the Pope without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting such Sacrilege as deserves to be punished with Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication?</p>
            <p>Nor is this a matter meerly Politick as <hi>Monsieur Talon</hi> pretends, where Religion has nothing to do: for the matter it self cannot be a Prophane, but must be a Sacred thing. For, let the Pope have acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that Sovereignty in <hi>Rome</hi> in what manner you will, he and his Predecessours have enjoyed it many Ages, and our Adversaries must of necessity grant that that Sovereignty changed its State and Condition from the very first moment in which it was given and Consecrated to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205164:20"/>God, and of a Prophane, became a Sacred thing, and therefore even according to the Canons of the Councils held in <hi>France,</hi> and Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated only by Kings as I mentioned above, the Usurpation of that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Sovereignty is Sacrilegious, and may be punished with Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</p>
            <p>Therefore though <hi>Charlemagne,</hi> and the other Predecessours of the present King of <hi>France</hi> had given formerly to the Pope all that extent of Land which he now enjoys; though all the Sovereignty the Pope has in <hi>Rome,</hi> and the whole Ecclesiastical State came wholly from the Liberality of that Prince, and the Emperours of <hi>France,</hi> which yet the most Eminent Historians of <hi>France,</hi> and amongst the rest <hi>Monsieur de Marca,</hi> denie; I say, though it did, yet that Dominion and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty being now Consecrated to God, and given to the Head of the Church, without any limitation or reserve of right whatsoever to any Superiour Sovereign in the world, no Person in the world, can upon any pretence whatsoever Usurp those Rights of Sovereignty, and rob the Pope of a Right so many Ages possessed by the Head of the Church, without deserving to be treated like a Sacrilegious Person, and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surper of the Rights of the Church, of such Rights as no Person can meddle with, without incurring Excommunication, even according to those Antient Canons and Councils of <hi>France,</hi> which I cited above, and which the Pope now in his Bulls against the Franchises, did but only Execute and renew. And certainly if the Pope had not used those utmost endeavours, and interposed his Authority in the highest manner that could be, to put a stop to that Mischievous protection or Villany in <hi>Rome,</hi> he might have been thought to have betrayed the Rights of the Sacred See, and that power of the Church which God has trusted in his hands: and of which to God he must give an account.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>